Guide to the Paul Mushak papers, 1975-2015 RL.11548
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paul Mushak papers
1975-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mushak, Paul
RL.11548
3 Linear Feet
Paul Mushak was a professor, researcher, and internationally recognized expert in toxic metals and their effect on human health.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into two series. The first contains works authored or co-authored by Mushak, including articles, studies, and reviews.
The second series contains works authored by others. The second series contains eight subseries, divided by subject matter and sorted chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Mushak was born in Scranton, Pennsylvania in 1934. He graudated magna cum laude from the University of Scranton. He earned a Ph.D. in metalloorganic/organic chemistry and biochemistry at the University of Florida. He went on to do postdoctoral work at Yale University.
Paul Mushak began his career on the faculty of the University of North Carolina School of Medicine in the Department of Pathology from 1971 to 1993. From 1995 to 2010, he was a member of the Montefiore Medical Center-Second Medical University of Shanghai, China Collaborating Centers for Prevention of Childhood Lead Poisoning and a visiting professor of Pediatric Environmental Health, Department of Pediatrics, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, N.Y.
From 1992 until his death in 2016, he was a co-principal in PB Associates, a toxicology consulting firm located in Durham, North Carolina.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Paul Mushak Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2017.
Collection Overview
The first series, Writings by Mushak, contains works authored or co-authored by Paul Mushak. Much of it is related to the toxicity of lead and other heavy metals.
The second series, Other Writings, contains works authored by others. This series is divided in nine subseries by subject matter. Each subseries is organized alphabetically and then chronologically. These sub-series are as follows: Arsenic, Beryllium, Bunker Hill NPL Site, Butte-Silver Bow County, Coeur d'Alene Basin, Heavy Metals (Misc.), Lead, Mercury, and General Documents.
Drinking water -- Lead content; Toxicity testing; Mercury; Water -- Mercury content; Heavy metals -- Bioaccumulation; Environmental toxicology; Toxicological chemistry; University of North Carolina -- Faculty; United States. Environmental Protection Agency; History of Medicine Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
- Writing by Mushak, 1997-2006; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Writings authored or co-authored by Mushak, including papers, reviews, and studies.
  - A Comparative Perspective on Lead and Mercury, 1997; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Report prepared for the EPA entitled: "A Comprehensive Historical and Scientific Analysis of Lead and Mercury as Public and Ecological Health Issues" co-authored with Betty Mushak
  - Lead-Blood Interactions, 2000 (Box 1)
    Paper entitled: "Lead-Blood Interactions and the Modeling of Lead's impact on Human Populations"
  - Arsenic Literature Review, 2001 (Box 1)
    Paper entitled: "Three Newly Published Scientific Studies on Arsenic Show it is Even More Toxic than EPA Assumed"
  - Lead Exposure Study, 2001 (Box 1)
    Lead-Nutrition Interactions in Lead Exposure and Toxicity in Children in Latin America
  - Proposed Changes in EPA Paper, 2004 (Box 1)
    External peer review on paper entitled: "Proposed Changes in EPA's RfD for Barium"
  - Reviews of Risk Assessment Plan, 2006 (Box 1)
    Comments on OAQPS (Office of Air Quality Planning and Standards) "Analysis Plan for Human Health and Ecological Risk assesssment for the review of the lead ambient air quality standards"
  - Review by Mushak, 2006 (Box 1)
    Review of draft analysis plan: CASAC Review of the OAQPS "Analysis Plan for Human Health and Ecological Risk Assessment for the Review of the Lead Ambient Air Quality Standards"
- Writings by Others, 1975-2015; 2
  Research, reports, and other subject files collected by Mushak regarding toxicity of heavy metals. Series has been sub-divided by toxin or location.
  - Arsenic, 1979-2006; 1
    - Human Exposures to Atmospheric Arsenic, 1979 (Box 1)
      Report entitled "Human Exposures to Atmospheric Arsenic" by Benjamin E. Suta
    - Arsenic Analysis in Various Materials, 1984 (Box 1)
      Air Sampling and Arsenic Analysis in Relation to Slagblasting Operations
    - Arsenic Standards, 1986; 2 folders (Box 1)
      Review Draft of "Criteria Document for Arsenic Standards"
    - Scientific Advisory Board Review, 1993 (Box 1)
      EPA Review document: "Review of the Draft Drinking Water Criteria Document on Inorganic Arsenic"
    - Arsenic in Drinking Water Discussion Paper, 1996 (Box 1)
      The 1995 Decision not to Revise the Arsenic Drinking Water Rule: Two Case Studies by Mark R. Powell
    - Drinking Water Committee Notes, 2000 (Box 1)
      Notes to Drinking Water Committee's Arsenic Review Panelists at the EPA
    - Science Advisory Board Review, 2000 (Box 1)
      Science Advisory Board report on certain elements of the proposed Arsenic drinking water regulation vettor markup, two copies
    - Cancer Risk Assessment, 2000 (Box 1)
      Cancer Risk Assessment of Inorganic Arsenic in Drinking Water report by Allan Smith and Peggy Lopipero
    - Respone to Arsenic Report, 2000 (Box 1)
      Response to Comments Entered into the Record of on the Drinking Water Committee's Review Draft of the "Arsenic Report"
    - Wall Street Journal Article, 2001 (Box 1)
      Photocopy of article entitled: "Dangerous Waters: All Agree Arsenic Kills; The Question Is How Much Does It Take To Do So"
    - Avoiding Arsenic in your Meat, 2006 (Box 1)
      Paper entitled "Playing Chicken: Avoiding Arsenic in Your Meat" by David Wallinga, MD
  - Beryllium, 1975-1991; 2
    - Feeding Study on Rats, 1975; 2 folders (Box 1)
      Report entitled: "Chronic Feeding Studies with Beryllium Sulfate in Rats"
    - Feeding Study on Dogs, 1976 (Box 1)
      Report entitled: "Chronic Feeding Studies with Beryllium in Dogs"
    - Health Criteria for Beryllium, 1988 (Box 1)
      Report entitled: "International Programme on Chemical Safety Environmental Health Criteria for Beryllium"
    - EPA Report on Beryllium, 1991 (Box 1)
      EPA Report entitled: "Drinking Water Criteria Document for Beryllium" prepared for Health and Ecological Criteria Division, Office of Science and Technology, and Office of Water
  - Bunker Hill NPL Site, 1986-2002; 3
    - "Kellog Revisited" Recommendations, 1986 (Box 1)
      Recommendations and guildelines for reducing children's lead absorbtion in the Bunker Hill NPL Site
    - Assessment of Lead Health and Intervention, 1993 (Box 1)
      Report entitled: "Assessment of Lead Health INtervention and Source Removal Efforts, 1985-1993"
    - Cleanup of the Bunker Hill Superfund Site, 1994 (Box 1)
      EPA Brochure: "Cleanup of the Bunker HIll Superfund Site: An Overview
    - Bunker Hill Institutional Controls Program, 1995 (Box 1)
      Report entitled: "Bunker Hill Superfund Site: Institutional Controls Program; Barrier Design Criteria and Permitting Requirements"
    - Summary of Lead Health Intervention, 1996 (Box 1)
      Report entitled: "Summary of Lead Health Intervention and Source Removal Efforts 1985-1996"
    - Technical Memorandum, 1999 (Box 1)
      Memo entitled: "1999 Five Year Review Report Bunker Hill Superfund Site Populated Areas"
    - Final Five Year Review Project, 2000; 3 folders (Box 1)
      Report entitled: "Populated Area Five Year Study Review, Bunker Hill Superfund Site, 1999 Five Year Review Report."
    - The Bunker Hill Mining Complex, 2002 (Box 1)
      Legal document: "The Bunker Hill Mining and Metallurgical Complex Operable Unit 3 - Record of Decision"
    - Response Action Contract, 2002; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Butte-Silver Bow County, 1992-1992; 4
    - Final Report, 1992; 3 folders (Box 1)
      The Butte-Silver Bow County Environmental Health Lead Study - Final Report
  - Coeur d'Alene Basin, 2001-2001; 5
    - Feasibility Study, 2001; 4 folders (Box 1)
      Document entitled: "Human Health Risk Assessment for the Coeur d'Alene Basin Extending from Harrison to Mullan on the Coeur d'Alene River and Tributaries - Remedial Investigaion/Feasibility Study"
  - Heavy Metals (Misc.), 1978-2004; 6
    - Draft: Atmospheric Cadmium, 1978 (Box 2)
      Draft report entitled: "Atmospheric Cadmium: Popualtion Exposure Analysis"
    - Draft: Sources of Atmospheric Cadmium, 1978 (Box 2)
      Draft report entitled: "Sources of Atmospheric Cadmium"
    - Carcinogen Assessment Groups, 1978 (Box 2)
      Draft report entitled: "Carcinogen Assessment Group's Assessment of Carcinogenic Risk from Population Exposure to Cadmium in the Ambient Air"
    - Effects of Chromium Compounds, 1984 (Box 2)
      Study entitled: "Effects of Chromium Conpounds on Human Health"
    - Fate of Heavy Metals, 1986 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "Fate of Heavy Metals and Heavy Metal Complexes in Soil and Plants"
    - Health Effects Documents on Nickel, 1986 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "Health Effects Document on Nickel"
    - Selected Aspects of Exposure to Heavy Metals, 1987 (Box 2)
      Workshop summary proceedings: "Selected Aspects of Exposure to Heavy Metals in the Environment: Monitors, Indicators, and High Risk Groups" Presented at Joint Workshop of National Academy of Sciences (USA) and Council of Academies of Sciences and Arts (Yugoslavia)
    - Oral Dose for Barium Compounds, 2004 (Box 2)
      Final Report on the External Peer Review of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency's Draft Document, "Proposed Oral Reference Dose (RfD) for Barium and Compounds"
    - Recommendations on Barium Compounds, 2004 (Box 2)
      Charge to Reviewers for a Proposed Oral Dose (RfD) for Barium and Compounds
  - Lead, 1979-2015; 7
    - Lead Exposure in Human Subjects, 1979 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "Oral and Lead Inhalation Lead Exposures in Human Subjects" by Standly B. Gross
    - Childhood Blood Lead Report, 1986 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "Kellog Revisited - 1983 - Childhood Blood Lead and Environmental Status Report" by the EPA and CDC
    - Air Quality Criteria for Lead, 1986 (Box 2)
      EPA Report entitled: "Air Quality Criteria for Lead" Volume I of IV "Draft Final"
    - Air Quality Criteria for Lead, 1986 (Box 2)
      EPA Report entitled: "Air Quality Criteria for Lead" Volume III of IV "Draft Final"
    - Exposure of Children to Lead Paint, 1986 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "Exposure of Children to Lead-Based Paints" by Anne Pope of PEI Associates
    - Blood Lead Levels, 1986 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "Blood Lead Levels in Children Living in Lead-Based Painted Housing Units" by Anne Pope at PEI Associates
    - Acid Rain, 1987 (Box 2)
      Workshop report: "Human Health Effects of the Acid Rain Phenomenon"
    - Leadville Exposure Study, 1990 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "Leadville Metals Exposure Study" by Colorado Department of Health and EPA
    - Elimination of Childhood Lead Poisoining, 1991 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "Strategic Plan for the Elimination of Childhood Lead Poisoning"
    - Lead Poisoning Prevention, 1991 (Box 2)
      Program entitled: "Childhood Lead Poisoning Prevention: A Resource Directory" mixed_materials,box,2,,,2,Other Writings,1975-2015,7,Lead,1979-2015,Procedings for Lead Poisoning Prevention Conference,1991,,,,Program entitled: ""Proceedings of the First National Conference on Laboratory Issues in Childhood Lead Poisoning Prevention"" "
    - Preventing Lead Poisoning in Workers, 1992 (Box 2)
      Article entitled: "Preventing Lead Poisoning in Construction Workers" DHHS Publication No. 91-116a
    - Building a Lead-Safe Future, 1994 (Box 2)
      Program and schedule for Second Comphrensive National Conference entitled: "Building a Lead-Safe Future"
    - Controlling Lead Hazards in Housing, 1995 (Box 2)
      Brochure entitled: "Putting the Pieces Together: Controlling Lead Hazards in the Nation's Housing"
    - Screening Children for Lead Poisoning, 1997 (Box 2)
      CDC Publication entitled: "Screening Young Children for Lead Poisoning: Guidance for State and Local Health Officials"
    - Leadville, CO Soil Lead Levels, 1998 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "Bioavailability of Lead in Soil and Mine Waste from the California Gulch NPL Site Leadville, CO"
    - New South Wales Summary Report, 1999 (Box 2)
      North Lake Macquarie, New South Wales, Environemntal health Centre Summary Report on Lead exposure, remediation, and blood monitoring
    - Eliminating Childhood Lead Poisoning, 2000 (Box 2)
      Brochure entitled: "Eliminating Childhood Lead Poisoning: A Federal Strategy Targeting Lead Paint Hazards"
    - Interior Dust Cleaning Work Plan, 2000; 2 folders (Box 2)
      Draft and Final Draft of engineering plan entitled: "Interior Dust Cleaning Work Plan"
    - Interior Dust Sampling Project, 2000 (Box 2)
      Final draft: "Field Work Plan for the House Dust Pilot Project Interior Dust Sampling"
    - Clean Air Scientific Advisory Committee, 2008 (Box 2)
      Papers related to the Clean Air Scientific Advisory Committee (CASAC) Review of Proposed Rulemaking
    - A Public Health Tragedy, 2010 (Box 2)
      Report entitled: "A Public Health Tragedy: How Flawed CDC Data and Faulty Assumptions Endangered CHildren's Health in the Nation's Capital"
    - Estimating Incremental Health Effects from Lead, 2015 (Box 2)
      External peer review of EPA's "Approach for Estimating Exposures and Incremental Health Effects from Lead due to Renovation, Repair, and Painting Activities in Public and Commercial Buildings
    - Misc., 1991-2010 (Box 2)
      Miscellaneous documents, correspondence, and fragments related to Lead research and health recommendations
  - Mercury, 1990-1998; 8
    - Syposium on Advances in Mercury Toxicology, 1990 (Box 2)
      Abstracts from Symposium on Advances in Mercury Toxicity held August 1990 Tokyo, Japan
    - White House Mercury Workshop, 1998; 2 folders (Box 2)
      Workshop: "Scientific Issues Relevant to Assessment of Health Effects from Exposure to Methylmercury
  - General Documents, 1984-2010; 9
    - Recommendatinos for Drinking-Water, 1984 (Box 2)
      World Health Organization book: "Guidelines for Drinking Water Quality Vol. 1 Recommendations"
    - News Release, 1996 (Box 2)
      News Release from Maryland Department of Health and Mental Hygiene regarding lead in drinking water
    - Council Directive, 1998 (Box 2)
      Council Directive on the quality of water intended for human consumption
    - Misc., 1994-2010 (Box 2)
      Documents and fragments related to metal and environmental concerns